<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:id="modsecurity-migration">
    <title>ModSecurity Migration Guide</title>
    <para>...</para>
    <section>
        <title>Variables</title>
        <para/>
        <section>
            <title>Syntax</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Change to Unicode, with UTF-8 as the storage format</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Use the same escaping syntax as in JavaScript</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Generally tighten the syntax, specifying which characters can be used and
                        where</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add syntax to specify n-th element in a collection, starting from the
                        beginning or starting from the end</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Allow the comma operator to be used anywhere to retrieve only one element
                        from a collection</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Make the comma operator smart so that it changes behavior based on the
                        current context personality</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Other changes</title>
            <para>With IronBee, we are starting to build the list of variables from scratch, adding
                what is needed, as it is needed. We may support some of the missing variables in
                future releases, but there will remain a number of variables that only make sense in
                ModSecurity. In general, we are reusing the names of ModSecurity variables wherever
                possible.</para>
            <para>In some cases, variables with the same name will behave differently. This happens
                for two reasons. First, whereas in ModSecurity <command>httpd</command> provided
                certain values, in IronBee we have to do it ourselves, possibly differently and from
                a different starting point. Second, in some cases we determined that there is room
                for improvement in how variables are constructed, and we wanted to do the right
                thing.</para>
            <para>In this section we will highlight some of the major differences:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>todo</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Rules</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The main rule directive is shortened, to just <literal>Rule</literal>. All
                    other supported directives from ModSecurity also have the <literal>Sec</literal>
                    prefix removed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>In chained rules, instructions (known as disruptive actions in ModSecurity)
                    are specified on the last rule in the chain, not on the first; the rule metadata
                    remains with the first rule in the chain.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>There are no default transformations, which means that it is no longer
                    necessary to begin rules with <literal>t:none</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <literal>SecRuleScript</literal> functionality is now handled by
                        <literal>RuleRunExt</literal>, which works as an interface between the rule
                    language and externally-implemented security logic (for example, Lua rules,
                    rules implemented natively, etc). </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Run-time rule manipulation (using <literal>ctl:ruleRemoveById</literal> or
                        <literal>ctl:ruleUpdateTagetById</literal>) is not currently supported.
                    These features are slow in ModSecurity and we wish to rethink them before and if
                    we implement them. At the very least we will wish to provide a faster
                    implementation.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Changing rule flow at run-time is not supported at this time. This means that
                    the functionality of <literal>skip</literal>, <literal>skipAfter</literal>, and
                        <literal>SecMarker</literal> is not supported. Neither is that of
                        <literal>SecAction</literal>, which is commonly used with skipping.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>IronBee uses a simplified configuration model in which site configuration
                    always starts from scratch. Inheritance is used when location contexts are
                    created, but, unlike in ModSecurity, locations always inherit configuration from
                    their sites.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>There is no ability to update rule targets and actions at configure-time, but
                    we will probably implement a similar feature in the future.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>All rules that generate events must use the <literal>msg</literal> modifier to
                    provide a message. This is because IronBee does not use machine-generated rule
                    messages. In ModSecurity, machine-generated messages have shown to have little
                    value, especially as rules increase in complexity. They are often a source of
                    confusion.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Miscellaneous</title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The audit log format has been redesigned to support new features.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>SecArgumentSeparator</literal> is implemented as a personality
                        parameter (see <literal>PersonalityParam</literal> for more
                        information).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In IronBee, request and response body inspection is not tied to buffering.
                        Disabling buffering will generally not affect inspection; it will only
                        affect the ability to block attacks reliably.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In IronBee, like in ModSecurity, you can have a transaction blocked if the
                        buffer limit is encountered, but, you can also choose to continue to use the
                        buffer in circular fashion. In that case, IronBee will simply buffer as much
                        data as it can, allowing any overflowing data to pass through.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Features Not Supported (Yet)</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Content injection - will be added in the future</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Guardian log - will not implement this obsolete feature</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>XML support - will be added in the future</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Persistent storage - will be added in the future (with high priority)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Chroot support - will not implement this <filename>httpd</filename>&#8211;specific
                    feature</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>File upload inspection and extraction - will be added in the future</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Anti-DoS features are not supported, and we don't expect they will be in the
                    future</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

</appendix>
