<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:id="todo">
    <title>To Do Notes</title>
    <para>This document contains the list of things we want to look into.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reminder (to ourselves): We will not add features unless we can demonstrate clear need.</emphasis></para>
    <section>
        <title>Directive: Include</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Brian wants to support only Unix path separators (but why not just use
                    whatever works on current platform?).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ivan wants to consider syntax that would allow configuration to retrieved from
                    sources other than the filesystem (e.g., from a database).</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Directive: Hostname</title>
        <para>Add support for URI-based mapping.</para>
        <para>Need to validate domain names that we accept.</para>
        <para>Our configuration files are in UTF-8 -- do we want to support international domain
            names (and convert them into punycode)?</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Directive: Site</title>
        <para>Enable variable expansion in site names. The idea is to avoid overlap when managing
            multiple sensors. For example:</para>
        <programlisting>&lt;Site %{sensorName}.default>
    # Site definition
&lt;/Site></programlisting>
        <para>On the other hand, this type of site name manipulation can be performed in the
            management component. Why should a sensor care about what other sensors' sites are
            called?</para>
        <para>Sites should be viewed primarily as a way of identifying (and mapping to) real-life
            entities. They should be used to reduce clutter and map multiple hostnames into a single
            name, and to use different policies with potentially different group in charge of every
            entity.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Directive: SensorName</title>
        <para>Explicitly configure sensor name. If omitted, use hostname.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Directive: RequestParamsExtra</title>
        <para>Extract parameters transported in the request URI. The parameter supplied to this
            directive should be a regular expression with named captures. On a match, the named
            captures will be placed in the <literal>ARGS_EXTRA</literal> collection. A new effective
            path will be constructed (using backreferences?).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Variable: ARGS_EXTRA</title>
        <para>Request parameters extracted from request URI.</para>
    </section>
</appendix>
